### **DIEGO RIVERA GELSINGER**

Department of Biology • Johns Hopkins University • Baltimore, MD 21218 dgelsin1@jhu.edu • (323) 314-4077 https://github.com/dgelsin

#### PROFESSIONAL STATUS

### Johns Hopkins University - Baltimore, MD

2014-present

*PhD Candidate,* Department of Biology, Program in Cellular, Molecular, Developmental, and Biophysics (CMDB) Advisor: Dr. Jocelyne DiRuggiero

Research focus: Mechanistic insight into small non-coding RNA-mediated regulation of stress response in halophilic archaea from desiccated environments and metatranscriptomic discovery of sRNAs in halophilic microbial communities from the Atacama Desert.

### San Francisco State University - San Francisco, CA

2012-2014

Undergraduate Research Fellow, Department of Biology

Advisor: Dr. José de la Torre.

Research focus: Physiology and ecological interactions of thermophilic archaea and bacteria in geothermal hot springs across the globe.

### **EDUCATION**

### John Hopkins University - Baltimore, MD

Fall 2014-present

Ph.D. Microbial Genomics

#### San Francisco State University - San Francisco, CA

Completed Spring 2014

B.Sc. Microbiology, minor in French

### **PUBLICATIONS**

- **Gelsinger, D.R.** and J. DiRuggiero. **2018**. "The non-coding regulatory RNA revolution in Archaea". Genes; 9(3), 141 https://doi.org/10.3390/genes9030141
- Gelsinger, D.R. and J. DiRuggiero. 2018. "Transcriptional landscape and regulatory roles of small noncoding RNAs in the oxidative stress response of the haloarchaeon Haloferax volcanii". J Bacteriol; 200:e00779-17 doi: 10.1128/JB.00779-17
- Crits-Christoph, A., Gelsinger, D.R., Ma, B., Wierzchos, J., Ravel, J., Davila, A.F., Casero, M.C., and DiRuggiero, J. 2016. "Functional interactions of archaea, bacteria and viruses in a hypersaline endolithic community". Env Microbiol; 18:2064 PMID: 26914534
- Davila, A.F., Hawes, I., Araya, J.G., Gelsinger, D.R., DiRuggiero, J., Ascaso, C., Osano, A., and Wierzchos, J. 2015. "In situ metabolism in halite endolithic microbial communities of the hyperarid Atacama Desert". Front. Microbiol; 6:1035 PMID: 26500612
- Trujillo, G., Aguinaldo, P., Anderson, C., Bustamante, J., Gelsinger, D.R., Pastor, M.J, Wright, J., Marquez-Magaña, L., and Riggs, B. 2015 "Near-peer STEM Mentoring Offers Unexpected Benefits for Mentors from Traditionally Underrepresented Backgrounds". PURM.

### AWARDS AND FELLOWSHIPS

2019 2017	Invited Discussion Leader for the Gordon Research Seminar Archaea, Les diablerets, Switzerland. Best poster award, Gordon Research Conference Archaea
2017	Trends in Microbiology best presentation award, Gordon Research Conference Archaea
2015	1st place award for JHU CMDB Annual Retreat Poster Competition, The Johns Hopkins University

2015	Institution Nominee for HHMI Gilliam Fellowship, The Johns Hopkins University		
2014–2015	Wyche Fellowship, The Johns Hopkins University		
2013	Instructional Related Activities (IRA) Grant, San Francisco State University		
2013–2014	CSU Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Participation (LSAMP), San Francisco State University		
2013–2014	NIH Minority Access to Research Careers (MARC), San Francisco State University		
2013 & 2014	NSF University of Nevada, Las Vegas-China PIRE Undergraduate Research Experience		
2012	Institutional Nominee for HHMI Exceptional Research Opportunities Program (EXROP), San Francisco State University		
2012–2013	–2013 NIH MBRS Research Initiative for Scientific Enhancement (RISE), San Francisco State University		

# **PRESENTATIONS**

January 2019	Mid-Atlantic Microbiome Meetup (M³), Baltimore, Maryland Novel insight in identifying and monitoring regulatory small non-coding RNAs in halophilic microbial communities from the Atacama Desert (Poster)	
March 2018	5 <sup>th</sup> Meeting of Regulating with RNA in Bacteria & Archaea, Seville, Barcelona Intergenic sRNA277.2: a post-transcriptional regulator of the oxidative stress response of the haloarchaeon Haloferax volcanii (Poster)	
August 2017	Gordon Research Conferences Archaea: Ecology, Metabolism & Molecular Biology, Sunday River, Maine	
	Transcriptional landscape and regulatory roles of small non-coding RNAs	
	in the oxidative stress response of the haloarchaeon <i>Haloferax volcanii</i> (Poster)	
October 2015	JHU CMDB Annual Research Retreat, Saint Michaels, Maryland Surviving in Extreme Environments by Regulating the	
	Oxidative Stress Response in Haloarchaea (Poster)	
July 2015	Gordon Research Conferences Archaea: Ecology, Metabolism & Molecular Biology, Sunday River, Maine	
	Small RNA-mediated Regulation of Stress Response in Haloarchaea (Invited Talk)	
April 2014	ASBMB Annual Meeting, San Diego, California	
	Chemical inhibition of ammonia oxidation in the thermophilic nitrifying	
	archaeon Nitrosocaldus yellowstonii (Poster)	
January 2014	CSUPERB Annual Meeting, Santa Clara, California	
	Chemical inhibition of ammonia oxidation in the thermophilic nitrifying archaeon <i>Nitrosocaldus yellowstonii</i> (Poster)	
June 2013	Symposium: China-US Collaborative Research on Life in Terrestrial Geothermal	
	Springs, Yunnan University, Kunming, China	
	Inhibition of Ammonia Oxidation in the Thermophilic Ammonia-Oxidizing	
	Archaeon Nitrosocaldus yellowstonii (Poster)	
May 2013	15th Annual COSE Student Project Showcase, San Francisco State University	
	Inhibition of Ammonia Oxidation in the Thermophilic Ammonia-Oxidizing Archaeon Nitrosocaldus yellowstonii (Poster)	
August 2012	SFSU Undergraduate Summer Research Symposium, San Francisco State University Nitrosocaldus yellowstonii: Ammonia Oxidation at Low NH <sub>3</sub> Concentrations (Talk)	

# RELEVANT EXPERIENCE

Currently using high throughput sequencing techniques (metagenomics/transcriptomics/translational profiling) to probe microbial dynamics of hypersaline endolithic communities in the Atacama Desert, Chile. I am using bioinformatic approaches to identify novel small non-coding RNAs that regulate stress response in haloarchaea found in these endolithic communities to confer adaptation to such extreme environments. I am doing this using a two-pronged approach: (1) studying the regulation of the oxidative stress response of a cultured representative of the endolithic communities, *Haloferax volcanii*, in order to use genetics to elucidate a mechanistic actions of sRNAs, and (2) development of a bioinformatic program, SnapT (<a href="https://github.com/dgelsin/SnapT">https://github.com/dgelsin/SnapT</a>), to identify and track sRNAs *in situ* over temporal scales in the endolithic communities. After *in silico* analysis, results have been validated with *in vivo* and *in situ* experiments such as qPCR, radiocarbon chasing, northern blots, and genetic manipulations. This work has culminated into a publication (see PUBLICATIONS) and three more in preparation. Current and future work includes establishing the direct mechanistic action of the most up-regulated sRNA in *Haloferax volcanii* (robust phenotypes in mutant, ectopic rescue) by determining its targets and regulatory processes.

### Undergraduate Research Scholar - San Francisco State U. Microbial ecology

2012-2014

Employed molecular, microbiological, and bioinformatic techniques to investigate the physiology and microbial interactions of nitrifying thermophilic archaea in geothermal springs. Major projects included: 1) transcriptional response to low and high substrate (NH<sub>3</sub>) concentrations in AOA, 2) chemical inhibition of thermophilic AOA ammonia oxidation activity, and 3) exploring the physiology, genomics, and evolutionary relationship between novel thermophilic AOA from Chinese hot springs.

## Summer Researcher Scholar - Tongji U. Shanghai, China, Biogeochemistry

August 2013 & 2014

Employed organic chemistry and isotopic techniques to investigate carbon metabolism of AOA. Used a variety of <sup>13</sup>C-labeled carbon compounds in hot spring microcosms and extracted lipid biomarkers to use in conjunction with Liquid Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry and Gas Chromatography-Infrared-Mass Spectrometry.

### FIELD WORK

Atacama Desert, Chile (2 trips)

January 2016 & February 2017

In collaboration with the NASA ARADS team we tested the capabilities of new rover technology to drill and collect deep subsurface samples for microbial phylogenetic and functional analysis. In addition, I did independent research on the dynamic metabolic capabilities of the endolithic microbial communities occupying halite nodules using *in situ* RNA acquisition and sequencing approaches.

Tengchong, Yunnan, China

July 2013

Participated in a collaborative NSF research project, Partnerships in International Research and Education (PIRE), to assess the ammonia oxidizing archaeal (AOA) diversity and investigate their metabolism and physiology in high temperature hydrothermal environments.

## PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT WORKSHOPS

CMDB Bioinformatics Bootcamp, Johns Hopkins University

Fall 2014

Week intensive course on big data analysis, Python scripting, and biostatistics taught by Galaxy founder Dr. James Taylor.

Bioinformatics Programming Group, San Francisco State University

Fall 2013

Learned Unix and became familiar with regular expressions, scripting, Python, and R.

## SYNERGISTIC ACTIVITIES (EDUCATIONAL AND OUTREACH)

2017 Designed and taught a lecture on microbial genomics and

bioinformatics to undergraduates in the Microbiology course

at the Johns Hopkins University Homewood Biology Department

2017 Laboratory Sustainability Representative of a pilot sustainability

	project at JHU to make laboratories more green and sustainable	
2016-present	Lead member of the graduate student group Teachers and Researchers United (TRU) in order to promote better conditions for graduate students at JHU	
2016	Invited and taught a bioinformatics lecture at the Halophiles 2016 meeting	
2016	Invited and taught Quantitative Biology Bootcamp to Master Students at the University of Puerto Rico Mayaguez Campus	
2016	Mentor for an undergraduate (Aldo Salazar Morales) recipient of the NSF REU	
2016	Teacher's Assistant in Cell Biology	
2015-present	Executive lead position of the Mentoring to Inspire Diversity in Science (MInDS) group at the Department of Biology, the Johns Hopkins University. MInDS is a peer-mentorship and outreach group for graduate students the in the CMDB program at JHU	
2015	Mentor in STEM Achievement in Baltimore Elementary Schools (SABES)	
2015	Teacher's Assistant in Biochemistry	
2012–2014	Mentor in Biology Undergraduate Mentoring Program (BUMP) which partners successful upper division biology majors with entering biology majors to provide them with guidance and advice. Influential in shaping the direction of the program and bringing other students into research	

# STUDENT MENTORSHIP

Rahul Reddy	Undergraduate student	09/2014 – to date
Kevin Maciuba	CMDB PhD rotation student	Fall 2015
Gherman Uritskiy	CMDB PhD rotation student	Spring 2016
Aldo Morales	REU undergraduate (Puerto Rico)	Summer 2016
Ariel Parker	CMDB PhD rotation student	Fall 2016
Neta Shwartz	CMDB PhD rotation student	Winter 2016
Katherine Huffer	CMDB PhD rotation student	Fall 2017
Michelle Biederman	CMDB PhD rotation student	Winter 2017
Anthony Mclean	CMDB PhD rotation student	Spring 2018
Kathleen Whittington	Undergraduate student	03/2018 – to date
Diego Tanton	Undergraduate student	03/2018 - 08/2018
Emma Dallon	CMDB PhD rotation student	Fall 2018
Grace Tamoefolau	CMDB PhD rotation student	Fall 2018
Sarah (Katie) Farney	CMDB PhD rotation student	Winter 2018

# LANGUAGES

Fluency in Spanish (mother tongue) and French (advanced to intermediate).